Armen Pischdotchian | Academic Tech Mentor

Location: Massachusetts Telephone: 617-699-6532

Email: apischdo@us.ibm.com and pischdotchiana@wit.edu

Professional profile

My current role entails four facets: first, is to learn and this is done by working with highly engaged team that include developers, tech sellers, and even external resources; second, develop assets including code patterns, documentation and videos uploaded to GitHub; third, to engage with universities in my region and while wearing a sales cap, invite them to consider partnering with IBM's academic arm to address the skills gap; and forth, enable academics and clients during on site engagements or online webinars as an advocate of open source and cloud technologies.

In conjunction with my work at IBM, I am also an **Adjunct Professor at Wentworth Institute of Technology** in Boston. During my Tuesday night classes, the students embark on a wonderful journey of artificial intelligence and data science.

Career summary

April 2013 - Present

IBM, Watson Solutions: Littleton and Cambridge offices in MA Academic Tech Mentor

Outline

In a typical university engagement, I begin by lecturing and demystifying the statistics (regression, classification) and the calculus (neural networks) used in machine learning models, which often leads to conducting workshops using Watson and Data Science services on IBM Cloud. In that capacity along with my team mates, I also participate as an embed mentor in hackathons. Often, universities that work closely with start-ups, incubators or other affiliates, use the campus setting as the development arena and me as mentor or solution architect in advising how to piece together various AI solutions from IBM Cloud offerings in building a proof of concept, or designing a new AI-centric curriculum for the school year. Additionally, I participate in panel discussions on EdTech Meetups discussing modern approached to education espoused by IBM's k-14 P-Tech schools that combine vocational studies focused on the information technology needs of the "New Collar" workers.

Key responsibilities

- <u>Lecture</u> at universities, meetups and conferences worldwide.
- Develop and conduct <u>workshops</u> that depict sample solutions as envisioned by student or client use cases. These workshops include coding in Python in Jupyter Notebooks.
- Run university <u>hackathons</u> including judging those hackathons.
- Participate as SME in building <u>Udacity</u> course on NLP.
- Participate as SME in building <u>Treehouse</u> course on chatbots
- Participate as SME in building the entire course for the AI Analyst role in <u>Skills Academy</u>.
- Developed course while in Dubai for Digital Nation Africa launched in April 2018.
- Mentored AI competitions, notably at <u>CUNY College</u> in NYC (at the 28-minute mark).
- Keynote speaker for the <u>IBM-MIT</u> hackathon followed by Watson workshops.
- Publish articles on the medium.com
- Advisory Board Member for Udacity AI and Data Science Initiative, building a modern industry-based curriculum for the adult learner in the field of Data Science in conjunction with advisors from Google, Facebook and Stanford University.

June 2002 – March 2013 IBM Tivoli, Littleton, MA Senior Enablement Specialist

Outline

I began my career at IBM as course developer for the Maximo, asset management product. This led to internal enablement culminating to running workshops for asset management companies as they migrated their meta data from test to dev to production.

Key responsibilities

- Responsible for creating both functional and systems related courses for the IBM Maximo product.
- These initiatives require product installation and knowledge of VMware technologies.
- Conducted proof of concept for various customers such as Alcatel Lucent (Paris), FMC Corporation, subsea exploration (Norway).
- My expertise was in migrating configuration content from development environments to testing and production using a tool known as Maximo Migration Manager.

Key achievements/projects

Published author of IBM Redbooks: Migration Use Cases with the Migration Manager Version 7.5 SG24-8132-00 http://www.redbooks.ibm.com/abstracts/sg248132.html?Open

July 1995 – June 2002 Teradyne Inc., Boston, MA Senior Technical Writer

Outline

Promoted to Senior Technical Writer in July 1999. Within this new capacity, managed a staff of two writers.

Shifted focus from in-circuit test instruments to optical inspection systems, gaining valuable knowledge about metrology, calibration, and optics and its interface with intelligent software.

Spearheaded single-sourcing efforts by initiating the database-approach to information management versus the traditional document-oriented approach.

Trained in XML technologies and creation of XSLT rules-based documents, began architecting the path to parsing XML documents via DOM software and rendering multi-file-format documents that serve cross-functional purposes.

Prepared reference-based training material for students and scripts for instructors. The training material is used by field application engineers to train customers on the AOI system and the role it plays in an SMT (Surface Mount Technology) line.

Education and qualifications

- ➤ MBA, Computer Information Systems Bentley University, Waltham, MA 2003
- MA, Technical and Professional Writing, CS Northeastern University, Boston, MA 1996
- BA, Organizational and Behavioral Psychology Boston University, Boston, MA 1985

Deep Learning Fundamentals

https://courses.cognitiveclass.ai/certificates/b02ea1d7406245d597ac5fb884a01dce

Build your Own Chatbot

https://courses.cognitiveclass.ai/certificates/7c053f0497cc47b097c9efc094d86b16

Data Science Foundation

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/399c43b6-f714-416e-b71f-7731a9c55edc

IBM Certified Exam Developer 2016 Level 1

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/63ee0291-7bb3-493b-8704-a34467c9628e

IBM Certified Application Developer - Watson V3 Certification

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/6265305b-a027-4255-bd1a-bb523f0e0075

Enterprise Design Thinking

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/98ff1123-0f45-4c83-9a0e-3674cc0f49c9

Data Science Orientation

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/9e75c0c6-d636-4f66-9eac-5a54d16f8633

IBM Blockchain Essentials

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/ba808922-d816-4fd3-8e44-bedec49adade

IBM Blockchain Developer

https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/cb219a00-4694-4dbf-90f7-25117ca2d217

IBM Certified Solution Advisor – Maximo Asset Management Solutions V3 License SR9046178

Distinguished Toast Master

Toastmasters International: Sep 1997 – Present. License Boston Chapter, September 30, 1997

For additional pictures and stories please see me on **Twitter**.